Rom Landau Papers
Rom Landau Papers
1927-1979
Landau, Rom, 1899-1974.
12.5 linear ft.
Papers of the British author, educator, biographer, Arabist. Correspondence (1927-1974); writings, including lectures on Morocco and Islamic culture in general, typescript essays, diaries; book reviews; photographs memorabilia; recordings of songs, music and dance of Morocco and other countries, and of interviews and lectures.
149120
Biographical History
Rom Landau (1899-1974) was a sculptor, author, educator and Arabist. Although born in Poland, he became a British citizen and served as a volunteer in the Royal Air Force during World War II. His particular area of interest was Morocco, and he authored numerous works about Morocco and the Middle East, mainly in the 1950s and 1960s. He taught Islamic Studies at the College of the Pacific in Stockton, CA, and was also an artist and art critic. His extensive knowledge of Arabic issues earned him a place on the Arab committee of the Intelligence Department of the British Foreign Office.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Portions of this collection, particularly Landau's personal journals, contain representations of racial and ethnic prejudices that were conventional during Landau's life, although no less harmful and inaccurate than they are today. This material is preserved and presented for its historic and research value. Researchers may find some of this content objectionable.
The Rom Landau Papers contains the papers of the British author, artist, educator, and Arabist. Although Landau's particular interest was Morocco, the collection also includes material on Algeria, Jordan, Iraq, Israel, Syria, Lebanon, Turkey and Palestine.
The collection is divided into six series. Biographical data and public recognition comprises short excerpts of biographical information, instances where Landau was mentioned in the press, etc. Correspondence contains business (1927-1974), personal (1972-1974) and legal material. Writings and art consists of Landau’s papers, manuscripts, lectures, notes, and speeches on the Middle East, political intelligence, religion, and other topics; it also includes a small selection of Landau’s sculpture and a copy of his book, God Is My Adventure. Printed material contains brochures for the University of the Pacific. Memorabilia comprises personal items such as Moroccan art, copies of Landau’s books, a passport, photographs, scrapbooks, silverware, and other miscellaneous items.
Recordings contains reel-to-reel tape audio recordings made by Landua of the songs, music and dance of various countries in the Middle East, and of some of his radio interviews, lectures and other speaking engagements, along with one apparently professional production, King Mohammed V by Leo Diner Films. There are also eight home-made recordings of opera singers and performances. Tapes relating to his Islamic studies are numbered and listed individually; opera recordings are not.
Arrangement of the Collection
Other than the division into the six series described above, the material is in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Landau, Rom, 1899-1974.; Arab countries.; Arabists.; Authors, English.; Berbers -- Songs and music.; Islam -- Study and teaching.; Islamic countries -- Civilization.; Islamic countries -- Study and teaching.; Africa, North.; Morocco.; Articles.; Audiotapes.; Book reviews.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Lectures.; Manuscripts (document genre); Motion pictures (visual works); Authors.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rom Landau, 1966-1974.
Inventory
- Biographical data and public recognition
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Assorted (Box 1)
  - Faber and Faber, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Letters from important correspondents (Box 1)
  - Arberry, Professor A. J. (Pembroke College, Cambridge, England) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Paderewski (Box 1)
  - Peace Corps
    - California State Polytechnic and speaking tours, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - in Morocco, summer 1963; original notes (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 1)
  - Publishers (Box 1)
  - Business, 1927-1963 (Box 1)
  - Business, 1963-1979; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Personal, 1927-1974; undated; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Legal (Box 2)
- Writings and art
  - Morocco, 5 folders (Box 2, 3)
  - Political intelligence, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Lectures (university)
    See also Memorabilia: Scrapbooks: Lectures (Package 5)
    - Arab history (Box 3)
    - Africa (Box 3)
    - Algeria (Box 3)
    - Arabia and Egypt (Box 3)
    - Iraq, Jordan, Libya, Israel (Box 3)
    - Modern Muslim world (Box 3)
    - Syria, Lebanon, Turkey and Tunisia (Box 3)
  - Lectures and speeches, general
    - Lectures at Commonwealth Club, 1936-1949; lectures and speeches (Box 3)
    - The supreme spiritual ideal (Box 3)
    - Palestine: Petition or... (Box 3)
    - The secrets of seven (Box 3)
    - Spiritual situation in the Near and Middle East (Box 3)
    - Speech for opening of debate at the Sorbonne (Box 3)
    - Lecture given at the Bishop's Palace, Norwich (Box 3)
    - Lecture at Lady Ravensdale's house (Box 3)
    - Lecture at the S. Finnes book fair (Box 3)
    - Radio address for BBC and West Sussex County Libraries (Box 3)
    - Opening address at the Bishop's Palace (Box 3)
    - Address to the World Congress of Faiths (Box 3)
    - Radio talks given at Radio Diffusion Rabat, Israel (Box 3)
    - Announcements of radio talks on KPFA-Oakland (Box 3)
    - The Moroccans yesterday and today (Box 3)
    - Announcements of radio talks on KPFA-Oakland (Box 3)
    - Lecture information from American Academy of Asian Studies (Box 3)
  - Artistic work and unbound manuscripts
    - Artist's work (Box 4)
    - Documentation for God is My Adventure (Box 4)
    - Documents, Pilsudski (Box 4)
    - Hassan II and Miss Hislop Has a Good Cry (Box 4)
    - Islam, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Manuscripts
      - Changed Lives (Box 4)
      - Kasbas of Southern Morocco (Box 4)
      - Last Thirty Years of the Peace Corps in Morocco (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      - Moorish Africa (Box 5)
      - Morocco (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Notes and interviews on first year of Moroccan independence (Box 5)
    - Notes, A Summer in North Africa (Box 5)
    - Notes and manuscript, A Summer in North Africa (Box 5)
    - Peace Corps in Morocco
      - First version (Box 5)
      - Second version (Box 5)
      - Final version (Box 5)
    - Works in progress (Box 6)
  - Bound manuscripts
    - God is My Adventure
      - Documents (Box 6)
      - Fourth version (Box 6)
      - Final version (Box 6)
      - Proof and postscript (Box 6)
    - Hassan King of Morocco (Box 6)
    - Paderewski
      - First version (Box 6)
      - Final version (Box 7)
    - Pilsudski (Box 7)
    - Pilsudski notes (Box 7)
    - Search for Tomorrow (Box 7)
    - Seven
      - First version (Box 7)
      - Second version (Box 8)
    - Thy Kingdom Come
      - First version (Box 8)
      - Final version (Box 8)
  - Literature reviews
    - Letter to Andrew, The Brother Vane, Islam Today (Box 8)
    - Love for a Country (Box 8)
    - Islam and the Arabs (Box 8)
    - The Merry Oasis, Human Relations, Odysseus (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Paderewski (Box 9)
    - Pilsudski (Box 9)
    - Search for Tomorrow (Box 10)
    - Seven (Box 10)
    - Sex, Life and Faith (Box 11)
    - Thy Kingdom Come (Box 11)
  - Articles
    See also Memorabilia: Scrapbooks: Articles and clippings on Landau (Package 5)
    - Deutscher Bote (Box 12)
    - Landau articles in British and American magazines (Box 12)
- Printed material
  - University of the Pacific, information, tourist brochures (Box 13)
  - Morocco, tourist brochures, clippings (Box 13)
- Memorabilia
  - Photograph albums
    - Poland, Germany, China, U.S.A., England, 1917 - ? (Box 17)
    - Italy, Tunisia, Switzerland, 1929-1934 (Box 17)
    - Poland, England, 1935 (Box 17)
  - Photographs
    - Morocco (Box 14-17)
    - United Kingdom (Box 17)
    - United States, 1960s; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Britain, Morocco, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Moroccan photographs with Mohammed V and Hassan II (envelope) (Box 20)
    - Rom Landau photographs of American Academy of Asian Studies (envelope) (Box 20)
    - Landau with King Mohammed V and King Hassan II (Box 20)
    - Landau sculptures, portraits of Landau, Landau in R.A.F. (Box 20)
    - Landau aboard H.M.S. Suffolk (Box 20)
    - Landau with King Hassan II (framed) (Box 20)
    - Oversize (Package 1)
    - Oversize (Package 2)
    - Oversize (Package 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Autograph book (Box 20)
    - Moroccan art (Box 20)
    - Mirror (Package 3)
    - Silver dish (Box 20)
    - Silver dishes (Package 4)
    - Glass bottles, 2 (Box 21)
    - Silver creamers, 2 (Box 21)
    - British passport (Box 21)
    - Plaque, 1963; from the Peace Corps Morocco Project, dedicated to Landau (Box 21)
    - "Doctor of Human Letters" degree, 1967; from the University of the Pacific (Box 21)
    - Photocopies of photographs and autographs, 1960; from trip on HMS Suffolk (Box 22)
    - Permission of the Queen to wear insignia of Officer of the Order (Box 22)
    - Ouissam Alaouite (Box 22)
    - Account of honorary doctorate granted 11 Jun 1967 (Box 22)
    - Clippings on Landau sculpture show (Box 22)
    - Press release on Landau donation, description of Landau books and papers donated to the University of the Pacific, Stockton, California (Box 22)
    - Notes on Landau books and papers (Box 22)
    - Information on 70th birthday (Box 22)
    - Information on book exhibit at British Embassy in Rabat, 1969 (Box 22)
    - Commencement Address at Kenitra American High School, 9 Jun 1969 (Box 22)
    - List of articles sent to Moroccan Room at University of the Pacific (Box 22)
    - Journal of trip to Morocco, 1937 (Box 22)
    - Moroccan journal (Box 22)
      This item contains representations of racial and ethnic prejudices that were conventional during Landau's life, although no less harmful and inaccurate than they are today. It is preserved and presented for its historic and research value. Researchers may find some of this content objectionable.
    - Scrapbook on Morocco (Box 22)
    - Leather folder (Box 22)
    - Visit of King Mohammed V of Morocco, 5 Dec 1966 (Box 22)
    - Press clippings, 1966; visit to Morocco (Box 22)
    - Address book (Box 23)
    - Date books, 19 books (Box 23)
    - Journals, 2 (Box 23)
    - Glass handles, 2 (Box 23)
    - Medals, 2 (Box 23)
  - Published books
    - English
      - Among the Americans, 1953; paperback (Box 24)
      - The Beauty of Morocco, 1951; paperback (Box 24)
      - God is My Adventure, 1935; 1936,; 1964; hardcover; 3 copies (Box 24)
      - Hassan II King of Morocco, 1962; paperback (Box 24)
      - Human Relations, 1968; paperback (Box 24)
      - Islam and the Arabs, 1958; proof (Box 24)
      - Moroccan Drama, 1956; proof (Box 24)
      - Morocco Independent, 1961; proof (Box 24)
      - Odysseus, 1948; paperback (Box 24)
      - Personalia, paperback (Box 24)
      - Philosophy of Ibn Arabi, 1948; paperback (Box 24)
      - Search for Tomorrow, 1938; paperback (Box 24)
      - Thy Kingdom Come, 1937; paperback (Box 24)
      - We Have Seen Evil, proof (Box 24)
    - Languages other than English
      - [unknown Arabic? title], 1907; paperback (Box 24)
      - [unknown Arabic? title], 1971; paperback (Box 24)
      - [unknown Arabic? title], 1974; paperback (Box 24)
      - God Heb Ik Gevonden, 1937; paperback (Box 24)
      - Sexe Vie Moderne et Spiritualite, paperback (Box 24)
      - Sexualitait Geloof En Leven, 1948; hardcover (Box 24)
    - Book jacket (Package 1)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Lectures in U.S.A., 1952-1953 (Package 5)
    - Lectures, 1953-1963 (Package 5)
    - Articles and clippings on Landau, 1955-1956 (Package 5)
- Recordings
  Recordings relating to Landua's Islamic studies are numbered and listed individually under the title or descriptive caption written on the box. The few recordings of opera singers and other music are not numbered or listed individually.
  - 1. Ahidora commentary (Box 25)
  - 2. Ahouash - Guedra (Box 25)
  - 3. Arab Contribution to Western Civilization (Box 25)
  - 4-5-6. Andalusian, 3 reels (Box 25)
  - 7-8-9. Berber music, 3 reels (Box 25)
  - 10. The Death of the King of Morocco, 7 Mar 1961 (Box 25)
  - 11. Guedra strip tease [?] "...if we can speak of 'Great' primitiveness..." (Box 25)
  - 12. Guedra commentary (Box 25)
  - 13. Himno Nacional de Marrvelos, played by Pacific Wind Ensemble (Box 25)
  - 14-15. Islam and Christianity, 2 reels (Box 25)
  - 16. Landau on present king of Morocco (Box 25)
  - 17. Moroccan constitution (Box 25)
  - 18. Moroccan national song (Box 25)
  - 19. Rom Landau on Morocco, 15 Dec 1966 (Box 25)
  - 20. Rom Landau, 23 Jan 1967 (Box 25)
  - 21. Talk on King Mohammad, 7 Mar 1961 (Box 25)
  - 22. Trouble brewing in Morocco, 27 Oct 1965 (Box 25)
  - 23. Xmas in Morocco, 1965 (Box 25)
  - 24. King Mohammed V, commercial film, Leo Diner Films (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous opera recordings, unnumbered, 8 reels (Box 25)